good afternoon everybody welcome good to
see you so today we're going to study a
arcane area of computer systems known as
floating point which is the way that
computer systems represent the real
numbers so you're all familiar with
decimal decimals you know something like
3.14 and there's a similar a similar
idea with with binary numbers okay so uh
so what what does a fractional binary
number like 1 0 1 1 point 1 0 1
represent and how does that work well it
works just like the decimal fractional
decimal numbers that you use to
so you have a in this case that they
it's a binary point and to the left of
the binary point you have bit position
to representing powers of 2 so 2 to the
0 2 to the 1 2 to the 2 so 1/2
I'm sorry 1 2 4 and so on and to the
right of the binary point you have 2 to
the minus 1 1/2 2 to the minus 2 1 4 2
to the minus 3 1 a and so on and so we
can we can represent any fractional
binary number using using this notation
where we sum each the bit at position K
times 2 to the K ok ok so it's really it
really works exactly the same way as as
with base 10 just just with base 2 so
let's look at some of these some of
these values so 5 and 3/4 we would
represent as 1 0 1 point 1 1 so this
this is before plus 1 is 5 plus 1/2 plus
1/4
okay so 2/4 plus 1/4 is 3/4 so 5 and 3/4
ok so that's pretty simple
2 and 7/8 is 1 zero point 1 1 1 so that
1 0 is 2 of course and then point 1 1 1
is 1/2 so 4 eighths plus 1/4 is two
eighths plus 1/8 okay so seven eight
and 1 7/16 would be one point zero 1 1 1
so the one to the left of the binary
point is 1 and then we have 1/4 plus 1/8
plus 1/16 so one 1/4 is 4 16 1/8 is to
16 and 1/16 so you add those after you
get 7/16 okay now notice that for some
of these numbers we this bit this bit
pattern 101.1 1 if we shift it to the
right to get 1 0.111 we've divided by 2
right so we've taken 5 and 3/4 and
divided it by 2 and it it works the
other way too if you shift to the left
you multiply if you shift to the left by
1 you multiply by 1 and these numbers
that are all ones to the right of the of
the binary point are these are numbers
that are just slightly less than than
one okay and so we'll well we want to
represent those will often will
sometimes refer to those numbers of that
form as 1 minus epsilon and epsilon just
depends on how many bits you have to the
right of the binary point so epsilon
gets smaller the more the more of those
bits you have there it gets closer to 1
and epsilon gets smaller the more of
those fits you have now there's a
there's limitations in this kind of
representation so first of all we can
only represent rational numbers of the
form X divided by 2 2 to the K we can
only represent numbers of that's form
exactly other numbers have to get have
repeating bit representations that can't
be represented
the finite number of debts that we have
in a computer system so for example
things like a 1/3 is that is this
repeating representation 1/5 and 1/10
there are other examples of that now the
other problem we have is that we can
only there's only so many bits to the
left and the right of the the binary
point so we're kind of if we put if we
move the binary point to the left then
we don't have as many we can't represent
as many large numbers we can only
represent small numbers but we have more
precision to the right of the binary
point so we can represent more
fractional values just the range of
those values will be much smaller
similarly if we move the binary point to
the right we'll have a larger range of
values but we won't build a represent as
many fractions okay so there's this
there's this kind of trade-off and
floating point is a representation to
that to try that that enables us to move
that basically to move that binary point
to represent sort of as wide a range as
possible with as much precision given
the number of bits the finite number of
bits that we have to work with so the
the float and floating point is this
sort of shifting binary point right this
floating this floating binary point now
up until 1985
floating point was just a disaster and
every computer manufacturer had their
own representation you couldn't and it
was just terrible because you couldn't
predict what would happen what would
happen if you moved your program from
one machine to another the behavior
would be different the rounding would be
different it was a very difficult
situation and people really computer
scientists in particular really disliked
floating point
in in 18 1985 I Triple E which is the
professional association for electrical
engineers introduced a and it's also a
very important standards body they
introduced a standard floating-point
representation called I Triple E
floating point which was then adopted by
all computer manufacturers so now the
situation is much better
everybody everybody supports the same
kind of floating point representation
which is what we're going to learn about
today so the floating point has the form
it represents numbers in a like a
scientific notation it represents
numbers of the form minus 1 to the s
where s is assigned it times a
significant M ok times 2 to some
exponent e ok so all of the numbers that
we can represent in floating point have
to be represented in this form so the
sign bit s determines whether the number
is negative or positive obviously the
significant m and sometimes sometimes
called the mantissa where the M comes
from the significant M normally is a
fractional value in the range between
between 1 & 2 and we'll see we'll see
why that is in a second and then the
exponent e weights the value by some
power of - okay so this is encoded in in
either 32 bits or 64 bits in the
following way the the sign bit s is the
most significant bit and then this is
followed by some number of by it by some
number of bits called the exp field
which encodes the exponent e of but it's
not identical to e it encodes e and
we'll see how that works and then
the frack and then and then that's
followed the remaining bits are the the
frack field which encodes them but isn't
identical to em now we I Triple E
floating point has provides two
different kinds of floating-point their
single precision 32 bits and so-called
double precision which is 64 bits
there's this funky Intel extended
precision which is non-standard and we
won't talk about it anymore
and so in the single precision 32 bits
you have one sign bit there's always a
sign bit you have eight exp bits and you
have 23 frack bits in double precision
you have 11 the XP bits and 52 fragments
now there's a number of different kinds
of floating-point representations the
sort of the default and sort of the
common representation is called
normalized so called normalized values
and normalized values are all the values
where the exp field is not equal to 0
and not equal not equal to all zeros and
not equal to all ones okay so everything
all zeros and all ones are special kinds
of numbers we'll look at a second so the
exponent this exponent e remember our
numbers are minus 1 to the power s times
M times 2 raised to the power e the
exponent E is encoded as this biased
value which is the called exp so the X
the exponent e is exp minus some bias
and exp is the value capital exp is the
value of the exp bits the bits in the
exp field treat it as a positive number
ok so capital exp is just you just look
at it as an unsigned
and seven bit in case of single
precision seven bit number
okay now the bias is 2 to the power k
minus 1 minus 1 where K is the number of
exponent bits okay so for single
precision we have 8 exponent bits so 2
to the 8th 2 to the 8 minus 1 is 7 so 2
to the seventh is 128 minus 1 is 127
okay so the bias for single precision is
127 and similarly for double precision
it's a thousand 23 okay so you just you
just have to memorize this this formula
the exponent e is the exp field
interpret it as an unsigned number minus
the the bias now this is a this is kind
of a strange thing the first time you
encounter floating-point it it seems
kind of odd right so why not I mean
we've already learned about two's
complement that's a perfectly fine way
to represent positive and negative
numbers okay and we have exponents that
are negative and positive right so why
not just use the exp field to represent
or why not just use two's complement in
the exp field to represent those
positive and negative exponents right so
it turns out that the reason that they
do this is that and if you think if I
think about this and we'll come back to
it but if we if we encode the the
exponent e using this bias
representation the smallest negative
exponent is represented by all zeros
okay and the largest exponent is
represented by 0 1 1 1 1
so the the smallest the swamp the number
with the smallest exponent if we were
just to compare the bits using it just
some kind of unsigned representation
just comparing the bits treating it as
an unsigned number by using this is this
biased representation we can just
compare two floating point numbers just
as unsigned we can treat the whole
floating point number as an unsigned
integer and compare two numbers and get
get a true comparison so the exponent
uses this this sort of biasing encoding
and then the significance is encoded
with an implied one so and this is where
the this is where the normalized in the
normalized representation comes from
that we're always going to represent our
numbers so M we're always going to
normalize m no matter what the number we
want to represent we're always going to
normalize m as one point something and
then we adjust the exponent accordingly
right so if if the value we want to
represent is one zero zero point zero
one we're going to shift it over and
it'll be one point zero zero okay and
then we'll adjust the exponent to
represent that shift okay so the V bits
in the frac field
xxxxX are all of the numbers to the
right of the binary point right so
there's always this implied one but we
don't even encode it we just throw it
away because it's always there all right
so this is a little trick just to get
one more bit for free okay so the the
xxx bits in the fraks field are all all
of all the bits to the right of the
binary point after one point the one
point and this is the so this is the
smallest fractal is all
Zero's which corresponds to a
significant of 1.0 and a fractal of all
ones corresponds to two minus Epsilon so
that's one swing one long-run 1 1 and so
on so let's look at let's look at an
example so let's look at how we would
encode 15 to 13 our favorite number in
two's complement and floating-point so
the if we represent that so it's an
integer and we represent it using these
fifths take my word for it correspond to
the integer 213 so now we want to
convert it we want to normalize it by
expressing it as one point 1 1 0 and so
on times 2 to the 13th ok saying the
same number we just normalized it so
that there's there's always this leading
so the significant m is 1 point 1 1 0 1
1 and so on the frack field is
everything to the right of the binary
point so we just we throw this we throw
this one away and we just take the the
values to the right of the binary point
and then we Pat it out with zeros to to
get the 23 bits that we need for single
precision okay so now we've got our
frack sealed the exponent so in this
case a YZ we're multiplying by 2 to the
13 so E is 13 so we want to represent
the value 13 using this biased encoding
so the bias is 127 and so the exponent
the value that the value of the exp
field should be 140 because if we take
if we take 140 minus 127 we get 13 okay
so 140 is represented using these eight
bits and that becomes our exp field okay
so the resulting floating-point number
and of course it's a positive number so
the sign bill is zero so the resulting
floating point number has these eight
the eight bits and exp field that we
computed by subtracting 140 by
subtracting 127 from 140 and then the
frack field are these bits that we that
we got here by just taking everything to
the right of the binary point so this
so let's look at this exponent just a
little bit more because I think can be a
little confusing
so so in our example if we want to look
at the range of exp so what's the
smallest value of exp what's the
smallest value of the XP the way no no
don't don't confuse the encoding with
the value of represents exp is is just
the encoding so what's what's the
smallest value of the XP 0 that's right
okay and the largest value is is what
remember it's what's the largest value
yep well the largest value would be
remember it can't be all ones right so
the largest value would be 2 to the 8th
minus 1 so okay so the largest value
would be 0 1 1 1 1 0 followed by 7 ones
ok so that's a 2 to the 8th minus 1 is
255 good
okay so then what's the range then of
the of e which is the actual value that
we want to encode okay remember use this
we have this definition so we have the
range of values for exp we have our bias
so what are the range of values for it
for e this is the actual exponents that
we're we're encoding so what's the
smallest exponent minus 127 good right
because that's zero is our smallest exp
minus the bias which is 127 okay so the
smallest value of e is is it's 127 and
the the largest value of e is so if we
take the largest value of exp that's 255
minus 127 128
okay so the the numbers that we can
represent using this bias notation will
have the smallest exponent will be 2 to
the minus 127 and the largest exponent
will be 2 to the raised to the power 128
okay so do you see you see what's going
on here so we have we have a range of
values for e here's the largest value
here's the smallest value here's 0 right
in the middle these are the values we
want to represent this biasing is like a
shift we've just now we're shifting up
by 127 so that now the smallest exponent
is represented by 0 okay any questions
about that
now these normalized these normalized
values always have this this implied one
okay which which when we get clipped
when we want to represent numbers closer
to zero that limits us right
so there's another type of
floating-point number called the de norm
de normalized value which which is
characterized by an exp field of all
zeros and in a normal in a denormalized
number or d norm there's no implied one
okay so the the significant m is
represented exactly is encoded
identically in the in the frac field so
there's no implied one and all of the
numbers are the form zero point
something something something after them
in the exponent value e instead of
remember for de norms we subtracted bias
from exp for d norms we subtract the
bias from one okay now you would just
use the the definition we use for
normalized numbers that would be the exp
would be zero so we don't do that
instead we Yi is 1 minus the bias and
then the significant is coded with an
implied leading zero instead of a
leading one like I like I mentioned so
so when exp is zero and also I mean we
think about it if if we only had
denormalized numbers we wouldn't be able
to represent zero right because there's
there'd always be a 1 in there so the D
norms allow us to represent zero and
they only allow us to represent values
that are very close to zero so when the
exponent is zero and the exp field is
zero and the frac field is zero then
this is the zero value
and so this is nice because all zeroes
represents zero which is you know sort
of what what you want now there is a
sort of weird thing though that if you
have a sign bit is one and then your
your frakkin and an exp or zero then you
have negative zero so you have this kind
of odd situation where there's a
positive and negative zero okay
and other values if the XP is zero and
you have a non zero frack then those are
the equally spaced numbers that are
closest to zero now there's a couple of
other special values when exp is is all
one and frack is all zeros this
represents the value infinity so this is
a value that that we get when is some
kind of addition or multiplication and
we overflow so in floating point always
overflows to the special value called
infinity the positive or negative
infinity so it's different from two's
complement rightward you sort of
overflowed and in this modular way back
just back it around into the range of
numbers in in floating point we just
overflow to the sticky value called
infinity and then then everything we do
on that remains infinity so for example
if we did a if we did 1 divided by 0 or
we or minus 1 divided by minus 0 we get
positive infinity if we divide one by a
zero negative zero we get negative
infinity the fourth the fourth kind of
special case special number is the case
where the exponent again is all once but
the frac is is nonzero in a non zero
value and this represents what's called
not a number so this is this is this
this lift handles cases with where
there's no there's no answer there's no
feasible answer for example if we
you know try to take the square root of
-1 what we'll get back is not a number
so 2 I think it's helpful to to
visualize these the number line now so
the we have positive zero negative zero
sort of right next to each other and
then to the right of that are the
positive D norms and then those then
those sort of transition into the
normalized numbers and then you have
infinity positive infinity they have a
similar similar situation on the for the
negative numbers and then negative and
positive nodded numbers so I think the
you know he's probably you've probably
discovered now that a really good way to
try to understand these American
coatings it's just to do examples with
only a few numbers bits you know if you
want to understand like for example in
tooth if you want to understand T min
and T Max and and how they relate to
each other just do a three bit two's
complement system you know imagine just
have a system with two's complement of
three bits and then you can just
enumerate all those all the
possibilities and you can see and then
you see where you know the T min is
actually one greater than T max you know
so if you add one to t max it actually
overflows into T min maybe a similar
thing for floating-point it's I would
really encourage you to do this just try
some simple examples with a sort of
tyent with a small number of exp and
frac bits so in this case we're going to
look at a floating-point system based on
I Triple E that has for exp bits and
three frac bits as always the sign bit
it's the most significant bit followed
by exp followed by frac
okay so this is this is identical to I
Triple E floating point except for the
size of that exp in fractions so it's
actually small enough that we can now
just enumerate these values and and now
you can I you can start to see why these
weird definitions for the exponent in
Donora and normalized numbers so let's
just look at so what we've done here
we've just with a signed bit of zero
we've we've just enumerated all of the
two to the seventh possibilities
possible combinations of exp and frac
fields starting with zero okay so when
when exp is all zeros
that's a D norm right by definition and
then we have the three frac bits or all
zero okay so remember the exp is all
zeros right so the four D norms the the
exponent value is 1 minus the bias our
bias here is seven okay so one minus
seven gives us a value for the exponent
of minus six so we're going to take the
frac the bits in the in the in the frac
field times so M is zero
so M in this case is zero times 2 to the
minus 6 gives us zero okay so this this
is our reference state representation of
zero and like I said it's really it's
nice that it actually is if we just
treated this as an unsigned integer we
just it would be zero okay so that's
kind of pleasing now let's look at the
very next number right the X exp is
still zero and we've just bumped up
track by one
okay so again it's it's a one minus the
bias which is minus six
and now this this frack field represents
this is 1/2 1/4 1/8 so it represents so
this is a value of amaz it is 1/8 so 1/8
times 2 to the minus 6 which is 1 64th
equals 1 over 512
so in this floating point system the
smallest nonzero number we can represent
is the denormalized representation of 1
over 512 the next smallest number is 0
okay now let's look at so let's take
let's bump this up by 1 so now we get a
we get a frac sealed of 0 1 0 so this
represents 1/4 so e/m is 1/4 that
significant is 1/4 times 2 to the minus
6 so 2 8 times 1 64 is 2 to the 5 12
okay so the the numbers were just invite
by incrementing this by incrementing
armored-car significant we're increasing
the numbers by 1 over 512 now the
largest d norm in this number system is
the case where the frack field is all
ones and so this encodes 1/2 plus 1/4
plus 1/8 which is 7/8 and then our value
is 7/8 times 2 to the minus 6 or 1 over
64 and that equals 7 512 so this 7 over
512 is the largest denormalized number
we can represent in this system and now
if we if we bump our number up by one
the the frac field resets to zero and
now the EXP field goes from zero to one
now because the EXP field is non-0 this
this is no longer a denormalized number
it's a normalized number okay so now
we're changing the definition of e from
1 minus the bias to exp minus the bias
so what's what's exp in this case 1
minus 7 the bias is minus 6 so lo and
behold it's the same it's the same it's
the same exponent as the previous
denormalized number so this is this is
actually very clever by the I Triple E
folks because you get the spirit you get
this nice smooth transition from de
norms to norms to normalize so you can
see that our our exponent e is minus 6
still and now our because we're taking 1
minus the bias 7 and our signature
significant now remember this is a
normalized number because the exp field
is nonzero just this the a fraction of
all zeros represents a significant of
one point zero zero zero okay so this
this normalized number this the smallest
normalized number represents is one
point zero zero zero which is 8 8 times
2 to the minus 6 which is 1 over 64
which gives us 8 over 512 so if we've
made this nice smooth transition from 7
over 5 12 to 8 over 512 and I'll do one
more I don't want to be so if we bump if
we bump keeping the exp field at 1 if we
bump our fracks deals from 0 to 1 now
this represents the the significant of 1
point 0
one point zero zero one which is eight
eight plus one eight so that's nine
eight times and then the value is nine
eight times 2 to the minus six once 1
over 64 which is equal to 9 over 512
okay
any questions about that
question back here okay the question is
why is why do you choose to bias that to
be 2 to the K minus 1 minus 1 well go
back to my my singer diagram here so
this is the range of the XP fields that
you want to this is the range of e that
you want to represent with 0 in the
middle okay and so you want to bias it
so that this is halfway 0 the smallest
exponent is halfway to 0 so you want the
bias to shift it up so it's the smallest
the smallest encoded the smallest value
of exp corresponds to the smallest
exponent right so 2 to the K minus 1
minus 1 is just giving you it's giving
you a value that's halfway between the
smallest exponent and the largest
exponent okay
that's good any other questions okay if
we take a like a little smaller six bit
format same thing as we did before just
different numbers of bits and exp and
frac and then we plot these on the
number line you can see that you can see
that the values are very dense around
zero so they're very spaced very closely
together and then every time you
increase the exponent by one the numbers
are spaced twice twice as far apart as
the previous the number the numbers that
are represented by the previous exponent
so you can see like in this little
example you see these these values here
are all equally spaced now these these
four values are equally spaced and
they're right next to each other and
then you see this jump in the spacing
that represents an increase in the exp
field by one and then it and then that
spacing doubles as we go out and you can
see it you can see it even better here
this if we if we zoom in these blue
values are the are these blue values or
D norms and then we have the the next
set of normalized values where the frack
field is one they're spaced the same
right we saw this when we kept
increasing by by one over 512 and then
we increase the the exponent by one and
the spacing doubles
okay so this like I mentioned this this
encoding has some some pretty nice
properties the the floating point zero
zero zero is encoded as integers here
which is nice and with the exception of
not a number with the exception of not a
number you can compare any
floating-point numbers including
infinity by just treating it as doing an
unsigned comparison so that's that's
really nice too
now if you when you add and multiply
floating point numbers right we're
dealing with a limited set of bits here
so if we take if we take two numbers
encoded as floating-point and we add
them together there's there's no
guarantee that we'll be able to fit all
those bits in the bits we have available
to us the there's no guarantee that
we'll be able to fit the bits and the
result so what so what we do in this
case is you can imagine the model you
want to have with floating point
operations addition to multiplication is
that you you add or multiply you do the
addition or multiplication and you
compute the exact result you just assume
that you have an infinite amount of
number of bits and then you round use
the technique called rounding to get it
to fit into the of the available bits
okay so the effect is like you're doing
say X plus y is getting the precise
value of x plus y at an infinite number
of bits and then rounding into the
available bits so let's look at this
this idea of rounding it this can be
confusing the first time you see it it
requires you need to think about it
carefully to get it right now in I
Triple E there's four different kinds of
rounding there's round towards zero
round down route or round to minus
infinity round up to which is rounding
it to positive infinity and then the
default case which is the only one
really we're really going to consider
which is round to the nearest even and
this is what I Triple E does by default
you can you can if you go into assembly
language you can change the rounding but
we're not going to consider it any more
yes question the
I'm sorry there is right because there's
one so the question is there a distinct
negative infinity and a distinct
positive infinity and there is they have
the exact same bit representation except
the most significant bit for negative
infinity is one and for positive
infinity at zero yes question white is
nearest even oh I'll show you
let me go over the others the question
was about nearest even yes greater than
big well that was me that was the
exception right today that's right so so
aside from infinity you can't do that
comparison positive infinity works right
but not negative so you're right that's
good point all right so let's look at
these rounding modes and I'll explain
live at the neuro Steven works but let's
look at so rounding towards zero what
we're going to do we'll use dollars so
we want to round to the nearest dollar
towards zero just anything less than you
just around you just round towards zero
so dollar forty would go to one a dollar
sixty would go down to one a dollar
fifty to one to fifty would go to two
negative 150 you round toward zero so
that would be negative negative one
round down towards negative infinity
it's similar the only difference is that
for negative one point negative a dollar
fifty you'd round towards negative
infinity which would be minus two
rounding up is the is symmetric to round
down the interesting case is round to
nearest even interesting because it's
what I Triple E floating point actually
uses so the idea here if you if you have
a value that's less than half then you
round down if you have a value that's
more than halfway between two dollar
amounts you round up
the route that nearest even part comes
when you have something that's exactly
halfway then what you do is you round
towards the nearest even number okay so
in in this example a dollar forty
because it's less than it's less than
half rounds down to one dollar a dollar
sixty is greater than half so we round
up to two dollars a dollar fifty right
in the middle we round round up to the
nearest even knock dollar amount which
is two dollars two dollars and fifty
cents we round down to the nearest even
right if we round it up it would be
three which is a odd number and - a
dollar fifty we round - we round down to
minus - two dollars so the reason we do
this the reason they chose this is that
statistically if you would imagine if
you have a uniform distribution of sort
of numbers they're going to round up or
down about 50 percent of the time so
there won't be a statistical bias
rounding up or down one way or the other
okay so that's the that's the reason
they did that now you can apply this you
can do this rounding to any to any any
any value so in the last example we did
it to the nearest dollar but let's
suppose we wanted to round to the
nearest hundredth using round two even
the default round - even mode so we want
to round to the nearest hundredth is the
second position this first do we have
tenths and hundredths so if we have a
value seven point eight nine for $9.99
that's less than halfway halfway would
be halfway would be any number that had
a five followed by all zeros so for 999
is less than that
so we would just round down to 7.89
even though 9 is odd the only the only
time we're going to apply round 2 even
is when we're exactly halfway okay our
next the next example seven point eight
nine five zero zero one that's greater
than halfway right if this if this was a
zero it would be exactly halfway so we
round up to seven point nine okay now
here's the interesting case where we
have seven point eight nine five
followed by all zeroes that's exactly
halfway so now we now we apply the round
to nearest even rule eight nine is the
negative an odd number so that doesn't
work so we round up and we do that
basically by adding adding a 5 here so 5
+ 5 is 10 and then that carries over God
to the next position and 9 + 1 is 0 9 +
1 is 10 so that carries over and so 8 +
8 + 1 is 9 so the result is set of
rounds ero okay is that clear you see
it's a very mechanical way when you
round up it's always it's a very
mechanical like that you always just add
the half way number in this case 5 and
then just just propagate it out just do
the addition and that will give you the
nearest the nearest that will round you
up to the nearest hundredth in this case
okay now the last case seven point eight
eight five followed by all zeroes that's
that's another number that's halfway
between between two numbers rounded to
the nearest hundredth so in this case
eight is even so we just we round down
and to round down we just truncate just
throw these bits these these digits away
and we get seven point eight eight so
there any questions about this
question back here yep yep that's the
question was if numbers that have the
same exp field will will those numbers
be equally spaced on the number line and
the answer is yes yes question all right
and things done thank you in the last
example deltas why'd you run it would
round up yeah the only the half way
values are always in this case because
it's base 10
the the half way number in base 10 is 5
and then so it's always the half way
number in this case 5 followed by all
zeros you always have that the half way
if a value is halfway between like 200
it'll always have that that form all
right now we can do the same thing with
with binary fractional numbers as well
now a binary number is is even if it if
the least significant digit is 0 ok we
only have two digits right so odd is 1
and 0 is even ok and the halfway so the
halfway value is going to be a 1
followed by all zeros ok that represents
exactly halfway ok so it's very it's
analogous analogous to the base 10
example except where the halfway value
is going to be 1 followed by all zeros
so let's look let's look at some
examples so suppose we have we want to
represent two and three thirty-seconds
and suppose we only have four bits to do
that in
okay well to represent that exactly we
need seven bits and so we have to round
okay so let's look at so we're going to
round to this two bits right at the
binary point and so let's look at all
the bits that follow that so since it
starts with zero this is going to be
less than halfway so since it's less
than halfway we just truncate just chop
those out and the result is 10.00 now
our next example is one zero point zero
zero one one zero so if we look at these
the bits to the right of these to the
right of the the bit we're rounding to
since it starts with one and it's not
followed by all zeros that's greater
than half okay so for the in this case
we have to round up and so the way we do
that is we take we take one and we add
it to this leftmost one right here and
just do the addition and the result is
one zero point zero one now let's look
at two to the seven eight this is
represented as one zero point one one
one zero zero
now here's that here's that half way
marker that we were looking for it's a 1
followed by all zeros so this is exactly
half way so now we have to round to the
nearest even number now that if we can't
just truncate because then it would be
an odd number right we would end 10.11
is an odd number so we have to round up
and we do that by adding we do that by
adding a 1 right here to this less
leftmost red bit we add one to that and
then just do the addition
and we end up with 11.00 which is three
so the nearest the nearest value to two
to the seventh eighth the nearest
rounded value is three okay our last
example two to the five A's
we have the same halfway marker again
one zero zero but in this case the the
hundreds bit are the one fourth bit is
zero so that's even so we can just
truncate we just throw those bits away
and the result is simply 10.10 that
makes sense so it's very mechanical and
mainly you just need to be able to
recognize that halfway marker and then
figure out if you need to round up or
down if you're going to round down just
truncate you're going to round up add a
one and just propagate it to get your
result okay now we won't spend much time
I just want to mention a few things
about multiplication in addition so if
we if we multiply two numbers so we have
different mantises significance and
exponents and suppose that the result is
M times two to the e the sign bit will
be the XOR of the two sign bits of the
two operands the significant M will be
the multiplying m1 times m2 and the
exponents are added right because
they're just by the rules of exponents
so if M is if M is greater than 2 and
this is a normalized number we have to
we have to we have to shift it and we
have to put it in the range between 1
and 2 by shifting to the right and
incrementing the exponent if he's out of
range then we overflow 2 to infinity and
then if if M has too many bits we have
to use round 2 even to fit it into the
available of fragments okay addition so
suppose we're trying to add two floating
point numbers conceptually what you do
is think of think of those numbers as
fractional binary numbers you want to
line up the binary points line up the
binary points then do the addition and
then a and then do the addition and that
if and then normalize the number so that
the normalized the significance of it's
between 1 & 2 and either do that by
shifting shifting right or left if he's
too big then you overflow and then you
round the the bits and M to fit into the
available for X field now remember when
we the first day of class we we talked
about we call these great realities that
intz aren't really integers and floats
aren't really reals so the and just as
just as just as we saw when we looked at
two's complement representation of
integers it's not exactly they're not
exact exactly like real integers and
operations on them aren't exactly like
real integers but they follow very
predictable mathematical properties okay
that are similar to integers but not
quite so the same thing holds for
floating-point numbers they follow very
predictable
they have very predictable mathematical
properties but there's somewhat
different from the reals and the the big
thing is is that the big big thing with
addition is that it doesn't associate ok
it's it's commutative but it's not
associative and this usually happens
when you have who you're dealing with
numbers that have very large dynamic
ranges so a big if you're trying to add
and subtract really big numbers with
it really little numbers you run into
this this problem with non associativity
so the the example was if we take three
point one four plus two to the tenth two
to the tensest so there's so much larger
than three point one four that when we
the bits that would be two to the tenth
plus three the point one four the the
bits that represent the three point one
four
you know there's bits way out here that
represent there's one bit out here that
represents two to the tenth and then
there's a few bits here they represent
three point one four and there's just
not enough we don't have enough bits to
represent all those so we have the three
point one four goes goes away so adding
a big number to a little number
essentially gives the big number and
then if you said you subtract that big
number you get zero now if we change the
the associate of the Association if we
take this big number and subtract it
from itself we get zero and then so the
result will be instead of zeros before
we get three point one four so other
than that you you have all of the things
that you would normally expect closed
under addition it's commutative there's
a additive identity of zero except for
infinities and Nan's there's there's an
additive inverse that you can take for
any number there's there's an inverse
that will give you zero when you add it
together and you get monotonicity
monotonicity between between values
except of course for infinities and ends
now multiplication has some it's similar
you get it's closed generally under
multiplication it's commutative but it's
not associative and it doesn't
distribute over addition and it's the
same so here you can see we're taking
two to xx x - 2 xx x - 2 xx and that
gives infinity
but if we if we reassociate and we take
I'm sorry to to the 20 times 2 to the
20th times 2 to the minus 20th well this
first multiplication is infinity and
anything anything you do with infinity
is just infinity so the result is
infinity however if we associate and
multiply to xx times 2 to the minus 20th
that gives us 1 and then x 2 to the 20th
until we get 2 to the 20th so the big
takeaway point here is that a floating
point floating point is an associative
ok now is that a problem
it's something you have to be aware of
and but generally I mean I I've done a
lot of scientific computing in
particular modeling earthquake ground
motion in Southern California so
basically we would we would build models
of Southern California in the computer
and then we would shake them and then we
would see how the ground moves in like
Los Angeles and those that that's
shaking we used a numerical method
called finite elements and it was all
used all floating points single
precision floating point numbers and we
never ran into a problem this with this
associativity right we would do we would
do operations in different orders we
couldn't always guarantee that we would
do the operations in the exact same
order but we never ran into a problem
with this because nature and generally
in general is kind of smooth right that
if you look at the you know if one part
of the ground is shaking like this and
you look at the next part it might be
shaking a little more or a little less
but you're not going to have like huge
differences and so we never ran into
those kind of problems but in some so if
generally if you if you're simulating
natural phenomena you don't often see
these kind of huge dynamic ranges but
other times you know if it's not non
natural financial maybe financial
systems they use floating point then you
might see this larger dynamic
the numbers and it might might become a
problem so as a programmer you just
generally have to be aware of this you
have to have a good sense for the
dynamic range of your numbers and you
have to keep in mind that if you if you
reassociate or change the order of
things you may not get exactly the same
exactly the same answer
okay so C gives us two different kinds
of floating points so they the float is
the I Triple E single precision and
double is the I Triple E double
precision now you remember when we did
casting between intz and unsigned values
back and forth the cast never changed
the bit representation it just changed
the way that in fact it never even
changed the the the what the how the ALU
manipulated those bits it's really just
a how we're interpreting and how we're
viewing those those values however when
you do cast between floats and intz and
doubles the bit representation changes
right so a cast here has a dramatic
effect on the actual bits themselves now
if we go from a double or a float to an
int it's going to it's just going to
it's going to truncate the fractional
part and give us the give us the the
integer part and then and then round to
fit oh actually no there won't be okay
so think about this how many there were
she said 23
23 frack bits and float and I forget
exactly how many in doubles anybody
remember it doesn't matter it's um it's
some number well no it doesn't matter
looks so for a float if we if we cast a
float to an int we're casting 23
something that we can represent with 23
at most 23 frack bits into a 32 bit int
so we won't we'll never lose so we won't
we'll never need to do any rounding
but double-precision has 52 bits okay so
they're there we may not be able to fit
the the represented integer into the
into the end so they'll they'll have to
be some rounding
sorry PowerPoint crashed
okay right now if we cast if we cast
from an int to a double there's will
have will have enough debt so we won't
lose anything right the 32 bits will fit
in the double precision frac field and
but int to float has there's more
there's more bits than an int that then
there are in the frac field will float
so we'll have to do some rounding right
so the so casting works the same way as
any other operation you can think of it
as just taking the assume you have an
infinite number of bits get the exact
result and then round it to fit into the
available disk all right so let's the
final thing I want to do today is sort
of test your understanding do solve some
puzzles to test test to understanding of
these properties of floating-point
numbers so imagine that we have three
values acts as an int F is a float and D
is a double and then we're evaluating
the CC expressions so X is X equal to
int float X yeah
how you can edit out the you can edit
out that other stuff
all right so what do you think if we so
if we take X which is an int cast it to
a float and then cast that back to an
int will that always be equal to X no
make as we lose some bits right we don't
have enough breakfast in float what
about if we take X cast it to a double
and then cast it back to ant well we
always get equivalent value yeah because
we have enough practice and in double
now what if we take a float F cast it to
a double and then cast it back to a
float well that always equal the
original F yeah what about the converse
though what if we take the double D cast
it to a float can cast it back to a
double no how about this how about if we
take F negate it and then negate that
again will that always equal F yeah
because we're just toggling a bit right
soon okay how about two over three equal
two over three point oh no because 2
over 3 is 0 and 2 over 3.0 is a is a
floating point value 2/3 the floating
point representation of 2/3 okay how
about if if the double D is less than 0
does that imply that D times 2 is also
less than 0 yeah even if no matter what
even if even if 2 times D overflows it
will overflow to negative infinity which
is less than which is less than 0
okay how about does the double D greater
than F imply that minus F is greater
than minus D yeah that's that
monotonicity right and again it's just
yes
- with people euros and float that both
are double
oh that's a good question I think it'd
be explode I think if we if you put
there's an annotation in situ to give it
a double but actually I'd have to check
that out that's enough yeah that's a
good question I don't know we'd have to
check off to go and look in the in the
see guide how about it is d squared the
double d squared always greater than or
equal to zero yes and how about the D
plus F minus D always equal F now
because of lack of associativity okay so
that was that was that was fun right the
floating points always fun so anyway
that the big thing is just to realize
that floats aren't exactly really reals
but they have very predictable property
and that they're not associative or
commutative they're not associative and
so you have to be careful about that
all right we'll have a good weekend
we'll see you on Tuesday